A Finding Aid to the Chaim Gross Papers, 1920-2004, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Printed Material, 1925-2004; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 3.7 Linear feet Boxes 10-14, 22, FC 24
  - Printed Material About Chaim Gross, 1925-2001; 5.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Art School Brochures, New School for Social Research, 1954-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Art School Brochures, New School for Social Research, 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Book, The Sculpture Relief of the Ten Commandments, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Brochures and Programs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Brochures and Programs, 1941-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Brochures and Programs, 1965-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Brochures and Programs, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 33)
      Oversized material housed in Box 22, Folder 2
    - Brochures and Programs, 1976-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Brochures and Programs, American Academy and National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1956-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Brochures and Programs, Educational Alliance, 1954-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1941, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1952-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1962-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1964, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Catalogs, Sculptors Guild, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Documentary Film, A Sculptor Speaks, 1956; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Copy of motion picture film original (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Motion picture film reel housed in FC 24
    - Documentary Film, Copy, Tree Trunk To Head (1938), 1995; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Improvisations: Artists Equity Masquerade Ball, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Improvisations: Artists Equity Masquerade Ball, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - NBC Broadcast of The Two Chaims, 1983; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassette Scotch UCA 30 videocassette (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - News Clippings/Articles, circa 1930s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - News Clippings/Articles, circa 1930s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - News Clippings/Articles, circa 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1934-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 20)
      Oversized material housed in Box 22 Folder 2
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1938-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 27)
      Includes photocopies of two photos of In Memoriam of Capt. Colin Kelly including one of Gross standing next to the plaster cast. Notes attached to the documentation indicate that the plaster was never cast, and was missing, presumed destroyed.
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1944-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1948-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1953-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1955-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1967-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - News Clippings/Articles, 1987-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, circa 1920s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1928-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1940-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1943-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1950-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - News Clippings/Articles in Yiddish/Hebrew, 1980-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Press Releases, 1963-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Reproductions of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Documentary Film, A Sculptor Speaks from Box 12, Folder 12, Archival Resource Key (Box FC 24)
    - Oversized Brochures and Programs from Box 11, Folder 33; News Clippings/Articles from Box 12, Folder 24 and Box 13, Folders 3 and 12, Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Printed Material About Others, 1942-2004; 5.2; Archival Resource Key
    Printed material about others includes announcements and catalogs for Moses and Raphael Soyer and others, and printed material on African arts.
    - Announcements and Catalogs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Announcements and Catalogs, 1942-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - Announcements and Catalogs, 1972-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - Announcements and Catalogs, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - Brochures and Programs, 1965; 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 35)
    - Printed Material on African Arts, 1957; 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - Printed Material on African Arts, 1974-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 37)
    - Printed Material on African Arts, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Printed Material on African Arts, 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases, circa 1960s-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Reproductions of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Sketchbooks, 1933-1991; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 6.1 Linear feet Boxes 14-19, 22
  This series comprises 115 sketchbooks produced by Gross between 1933 and 1991. The earliest sketchbooks are primarily figure and head studies interspersed with landscape sketches. Themes include the mother and child bond and models in acrobatic poses. There are sketches of Renee Gross with baby Mimi, Raphael Soyer, and Concetta Scaravaglione.
  Beginning in 1944 Gross's sketchbooks take on a much darker tone with sketches characterized by bird-like and serpentine creatures of a mythological nature combined with human forms, images of war, Hebrew iconography, and recurring motifs of subjects pierced with long shards and nails, many dripping tears. A selection of Gross's sketches from this period were published in the book Chaim Gross: Fantasy Drawings by Beechurst Press, Inc. in 1956. These types of images continue to dominate the sketchbooks through the mid-1950s, and begin to diminish thereafter. Sketchbooks from the 1960s are characterized by figure and head studies, Jewish iconography, and vibrant and colorful sketches of travels abroad. The sketchbooks from 1965-1966 includes sketches of William and Marguerite Zorach.
  "Fantasy drawings" reappear in the late 1970s-1980s, and the bird and teardrop motifs are revisited, although the drawings are less violent in nature. The 1987-1988 sketchbook includes sketches indicative of self-examination in the face of grief and mortality, such as those expressing Gross's grief on the death of life-long friend Raphael Soyer, and self-portrait sketches.
  Sketches are in pencil, ink and wash, and watercolor. Many are annotated with notes on art and addresses of friends and contacts. Sketchbooks include a handful of sketches by others including one by Eliot Elisofon and several by Raphael Soyer and Mimi Gross.
  Also found at the end of the series is a 1977 signed and numbered print (2 of 100) by Gross, entitled Happy Mother.
  Sketchbook are arranged chronologically with one sketchbook per folder.
  - Sketchbook, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook, 1934-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook, 1938-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Sketchbook, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Sketchbook, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbook, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Sketchbook, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Sketchbook, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Sketchbook, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Sketchbook, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Sketchbook, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Sketchbook, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1942 May; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, 1944-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1945-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook, 1948-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, France, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 14)
    includes sketches by Mimi Gross
  - Sketchbook, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, 1955-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, 1958-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook-Israel, Paris, Rome Spain, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook-Israel, Istanbul, Paris, Rome, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook-Amsterdam, Rome, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, Acapulco, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, 1962-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Sketchbook, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Sketchbook, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Includes sketches by Moses Soyer
  - Sketchbook, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook, Africa, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, Jerusalem, Israel, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, Paris, France, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, Paris, New York, Spain, Canary Isles, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, Paris, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, Yugoslavia, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook, Barcelona and France, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1971-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, 1975, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 4)
    Oversized sketchbook housed in Box 22, Folder 3; includes 2 sketches by Raphael Soyer and 1979 news clipping
  - Sketchbook, Jerusalem, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Includes sketches of Raphael Soyer
  - Sketchbook, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Includes sketch by Raphael Soyer and of Soyer by Gross
  - Sketchbook, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1985-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 6)
    includes sketch by Raphael Soyer
  - Sketchbook, 1986-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Includes sketch of Raphael Soyer day before his death
  - Sketchbook, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Loose Sketches from 1990-1991 Sketchbook, circa 1990-circa 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Loose Sketches, circa 1940s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Signed Print Happy Mother, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 19)
    Oversized print housed in OV 23
  - Oversized Sketchbook, 1975, 1979 from Box 18, Folder 4, Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Signed Print Happy Mother from Box 19, Folder 19, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 23)
- Photographs, circa 1921-circa 1990s; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 20-22
  Photographs are arranged as two series.
  7.1: Photographs of People and Events, circa 1921-circa 1980s
  7.2: Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1930s-circa 1990s
  - Photographs of People and Events, circa 1921-circa 1980s; 7.1; Archival Resource Key
    Photographs of people and places include portraits of Gross; photographs of Gross at home with his art collection, with family, in his studio, at the foundry, and at exhibition openings, parties, and gatherings in his home and elsewhere; and photographs of Gross with friends, artists, art collectors, and others. Portraits are by Linda Kleban-Kleineman, Marvin P. Lazarus, Arnold Newman, Carl van Vechten, Max Waldman, and others. Photos of Gross in his studio include at least two taken by Eliot Elisofon that were used in Gross's book The Technique of Wood Sculpture.
    Photographs of the Gross family include Gross with his two brothers shortly after reuniting in the United States circa 1921; family portraits of Gross, Renee, and their children; a photograph of Mimi Gross with Red Grooms and their daughter Saskia taken by Arnold Newman; and two photographs of Arnold Newman with Mimi Gross and Red Grooms.
    Photographs of Chaim Gross in the studio span entire his career from the 1930s to the 1980s and include images of Gross's Grand Street studio in Soho, purchased in 1963, and of his home and studio at 526 LaGuardia Place. There are photographs of Gross working on sculpture for the 1939 World's Fair, working on Six Days of Creation for Temple Shaaray Tefila in New York City, circa 1966, and with his sculpture at the Bedi-Makky Art Foundry in Greenpoint, Brooklyn. Photographs from the 1960s include some take by Dena (Dinah Rubenstein). One 1944 photograph includes an image of photographer Marion Palfi posing for another artist.
    Photos of Gross with others include fellow Educational Alliance Art School students Peter Blume, Elias Grossman, Leon Jackson, Elias Newman, and Anna Ostrovski. Photos of parties include photos from Chaim and Renee Gross's fiftieth wedding anniversary picturing attendees including Sally Avery, Estelle Kerkauf, Jack Levine, Arnold Newman, Warren M. Robbins, and Raphael Soyer. Attendees pictured at other parties at Gross's home include Emil Arnold, Maurice Becker, Leonard Bocour, Frederico Castellon, Nicolai Cikovsky, Joseph Floch, Ruth Gikow, Marsha Hersey, Leon Kroll, Jack Levine, Irving Marantz, Morris Nechin, Raphael Soyer, Sylvia Small, Stuyvesant Van Veen, Hudson D. Walker, and Sol Wilson.
    Photographs of art-related events include Gross participating in symposia, juries, art demonstrations, auctions, awards dinners, and other events and include John Hovaness; Adolph Gottlieb and Nelson Rockefeller at an Educational Alliance Art School celebration; Vincent Glinsky at a Sculptors Guild member benefit; and Golda Meir receiving the sculpture Mother Israel at a Bonds for Israel dinner in 1974.
    Gross is also pictured with art collectors and gallery owners such as Bella and Sol Fishko, Sidney Janis, Gus Newman, Warren Robbins, and Helena Rubenstein; and other prominent people including Barbara Streisand and Abba Eban, an Israeli diplomat and politician and a scholar of the Arabic and Hebrew languages; and Leonard Harris interviewing Gross for a circa 1967 television program.
    Photographs of Chaim Gross with artists include: Richard Avedon, Peter Blume, Hyman Brown (posing for Gross), Alexander Dobkin, Joseph Hirsch (possibly with Ernest Fine and Sol Wilson), Al Hirschfield, Karl Knaths (posing for Gross), Jack Levine, Louise Nevelson, Anthony Quinn, and Herman Rose. There is also a photograph of Gross with William Zorach, Helen Keller, and Anne Sullivan at a 1938 Sculptor's Guild outdoor exhibition in which Helen Keller is admiring one of Gross's sculptures. Photographs of Gross with Isaac, Moses, and Raphael Soyer include a portrait of Gross, Moses Soyer and L. Riebuck, 1924, by Richard Alan Fox; a photo of Gross with Arnold Newman and Raphael Soyer; and a photo of Joseph Stella posing for Moses Soyer.
    Photographs of exhibition installations include Gross's first one-man show at Gallery 144 West 13th Street; a 1939 Sculptors Guild exhibition; a 1957 Duveen-Graham Gallery exhibition; a 1959-1960 solo exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art; and a 1967 exhibition at Forum Gallery.